曾经
Once upon a time
我们生活在一个金融增长和繁荣的经济体之中
we lived in an economy of financial growth and prosperity
这被称作"大稳健"时期
This was called the Great Moderation
大多数经济学家 政府决策者 以及央行都错误地认为
the misguided belief by most economists, policymakers, and central banks
我们正在步入一个增长和繁荣永远不会停止的新世界
that we have transformed into a new world of never ending growth and prosperity
这段时期见证了稳健的GDP增长
This was seen by robust and steady GDP growth
受控良好的低通胀
by low and controlled inflation
低失业率
by low unemployment
以及受控良好的低金融波动
and controlled and low financial volatility
但2007-2008年发生了"大衰退"
But the Great Recession in 2007-2008
这次大崩溃打破了这一幻想
the great crash, broke this illusion
金融业损失数千亿美元
A few hundred billion dollars of losses in the financial sector
并进一步导致全世界5万亿美元的GDP损失
cascaded into $5 trillion of losses in world GDP
以及将近30万亿美元的全球股市损失
and almost $30 trillion losses in global stock market
而对"大衰退"的理解却是
So the understanding of this Great Recession was that
它完全是意外
this was completely surprising
突如其来 犹如上天之怒
this came out of the blue; this was like the wrath of the gods
我们无能为力
There was no responsibility
为了反思这些 我们创立了金融危机观测台
So as a reflection of this, we started the Financial Crisis Observatory
我们的目标是实时诊断金融泡沫
We had the goal to diagnose, in real-time, financial bubbles
并提前鉴别出它们的临界时间
and identify in advance their critical time
这一金融观测台的科学基础是什么呢
What is the underpinning, scientifically, of this financial observatory?
我们提出了一个理论 名曰"龙王"
We developed a theory called "dragon-kings"
龙王代表同类事件中的极端事件
Dragon-kings represent extreme events which are of a class of their own
它们很特殊
They're special
它们是异常情况
They're outliers
它们是特定机制所造成的
They're generated by specific mechanism
可能具有可预测性
that may make them predictable
甚至可控性
perhaps controllable
考虑金融价格的时间序列
Consider the financial price time series
某种股票 你最好的股票
a given stock, your perfect stock
或者说全球指数
or global index
你有这些上下波动
You have these up-and-downs
金融市场风险的很好度量
A very good measure of the risk of this financial market
是表示最坏情形的峰谷差值
is the peaks-to-valleys that represent the worst case scenario
你在最高时买进 却在最低时卖出
when you bought at the top, and sold at the bottom
你可以参考统计数字
You can look at the statistics
考虑不同规模峰谷差值的出现频率
the frequency of the occurrence of peak-to-valleys of different sizes
也就是这张图中所表示的
which is represented in this graph
有趣的是 不同幅值的峰谷差值中 有99%
Now interestingly, 99% of the peak-to-valleys of different amplitudes
能用具有普遍性的幂定律来表示
can be represented by a universal power law
这里表示为这条红线
represented by this red line here
更有趣的是
More interestingly
存在一些离群值 一些异常值落在红线上方
there are outliers, there are exceptions which are above this red line
发生频率要比预测值高出至少100倍
occur 100 times more frequently
at least, than, the extrapolation would predict them to occur
这里预计是基于剩余99%峰谷差值校准的情况
based on the calibration of the 99% remaining peak-to-valleys
这些离群值是由暂态依赖性所造成的
They are due to transient dependencies
使得一个损失接着另一个损失
such that a loss is followed by a loss
接着另一个损失 接着另一个损失
which is followed by a loss, which is followed by a loss
这种依赖性
These kinds of dependencies
在当今的标准风险管理工具中 很大程度被忽视了
are largely missed by standard risk management tools
标准工具将它们看作是"蜥蜴"
which ignore them and see lizards
其实它们应该被看作"龙王"
while they should see dragon-kings
这些龙王的根本机制
The root mechanism of a dragon-king
是一种缓慢成熟 逐渐趋向不稳定
is a slow maturation towards instability
也就是泡沫
which is the bubble
而泡沫发展到极致 通常会导致崩溃
and the climax of the bubble is often the crash
这类似于试管中水的缓慢升温过程
This is similar to the slow heating of water in this test tube
逐渐逼近沸点
reaching the boiling point
当水的不稳定性爆发时
where the instability of the water occurs
就会产生相变 由水变为蒸气
and you have the phase transition to vapor
这个过程 肯定不是线性的
And this process, which is absolutely non-linear --
不能用标准技术来预测
cannot be predicted by standard techniques --
是集体突发行为的反映
is the reflection of a collective emergent behavior
具有根本的内生性
which is fundamentally endogenous
因此 崩溃的原因 危机的原因
So the cause of the crash, the cause of the crisis
必须在系统的不稳定性内部寻找
has to be found in an inner instability of the system
任何微小的扰动 都会让不稳定性爆发
and any tiny perturbation will make this instability occur
你们有些人这时可能也意识到了
Now some of you may have come to the mind that
这不是和你们经常听到的黑天鹅理论相关吗
is this not related to the black swan concept you have heard about frequently?
黑天鹅这种鸟 欧洲人第一次看到后
Remember, black swan is this rare bird that you see once
天鹅都是白的这种固有认识就被彻底颠覆
and suddenly shattered your belief that all swans should be white
我们用黑天鹅理论来描述不可预测性 不可知性
so it has captured the idea of unpredictability, unknowability
认为极端事件根本上是不可知的
that the extreme events are fundamentally unknowable
而我所提出的龙王理论恰好同它相反
Nothing can be further from the dragon-king concept I propose
龙王理论认为
which is exactly the opposite
大多数极端事件都是可知的 都是可预测的
that most extreme events are actually knowable and predictable
所以我们有能力担起责任
So we can be empowered and take responsibility
对它们进行预测
and make predictions about them
让我的龙王烧掉这种黑天鹅理论
So let's have my dragon-king burn this black swan concept
根据龙王理论 早期有很多警报信号是可预测的
There are many early warning signals that are predicted by this theory
这里我将集中讨论其中一个
Let me just focus on one of them:
即带有正反馈的超指数增长
the super-exponential growth with positive feedback
什么意思呢
What does it mean?
假设你有一个投资
Imagine you have an investment
第一年回报是5%
that returns the first year 5 percent
第二年10% 第三年20%
the second year 10 percent, the third year 20 percent
第四年40% 这太了不起了 对吧
the next year 40 percent. Is that not marvelous?
这就是一个超指数增长
This is a super-exponential growth
不像标准指数增长
A standard exponential growth corresponds
指的是一种常数增长率 比如10%
to a constant growth rate, let's say, of 10 percent
问题在于 很多存在泡沫的时候
The point is that, many times during bubbles
这些正反馈可能出现很多次
there are positive feedbacks which can be of many times
使得之前的增长被增强
such that previous growths enhance
往前推进 提升下一次增长
push forward, increase the next growth
这都是通过这种超指数增长实现的
through this kind of super-exponential growth which is
而这种增长是暂态的 不能持久的
very transient, not sustainable
关键在于 这类模型的数学解
And the key idea is that the mathematical solution of this class of models
表现出有限时间奇异性 也就是说
exhibit finite-time singularities, which means
存在一个临界时间
that there is a critical time
此时系统会突变 会发生质变
where the system will break, will change regime
这可能是崩溃 也可能是达到平稳水平 等等
It may be a crash. It may be just a plateau, something else
关键在于 这个临界时间
And the key idea is that the critical time
它的信息包含于
the information about the critical time is contained
这个超指数增长的早期发展之中
in the early development of this super-exponential growth
我们很早就将这个理论 这是理论的首次成功
We have applied this theory early on, that was our first success
用于诊断阿丽亚娜火箭关键部件的破裂
to the diagnostic of the rupture of key elements on the Ariane rocket
我们使用声发射检验
Using acoustic emission
这些结构会发射小声波 对你"唱歌"
you know, this little noise that you hear a structure emit, sing to you
当它们受到压力 就会揭示出损坏的发生
when they are stressed, and reveal the damage going on
存在正反馈的集体现象
there's a collective phenomenon of positive feedback
更多损坏会导致更多损坏
the more damage gives the more damage
于是就能在误差范围内预测出
so you can actually predict, within, of course, a probability band
破裂会何时出现
when the rupture will occur
这个现在非常成功
So this is now so successful
被用于检验能否飞行的初始阶段
that it is used in the initial phase of can we be flying the flight
也许更让人吃惊的是
Perhaps more surprisingly
相同理论还适用于生物和医药
the same type of theory applies to biology and medicine
分娩 生产 癫痫发作
parturition, the act of giving birth, epileptic seizures
从怀孕后7个月开始
From 7 months of pregnancy
母亲开始感受到偶发的子宫收缩
a mother starts to feel episodic precursory contractions of the uterus
这预示着趋向不稳定的成熟过程
that are the sign of these maturations toward the instability
要生小孩了 这就是龙王
giving birth to the baby, the dragon-king
如果你去测量前导信号
So if you measure the precursor signal
你将能够提前鉴别出成熟前和成熟后的问题
you can actually identify pre- and post-maturity problems in advance
癫痫发作 也会以各种不同规模出现
Epileptic seizures also come in a large variety of size
当脑达到一个超临界状态时
and when the brain goes to a super-critical state
你会有龙王 它具有一定程度的可预测性
you have dragon-kings which have a degree of predictability
这能帮助病人处理这种疾病
and this can help the patient to deal with this illness
我们将这个理论用到很多系统中
We have applied this theory to many systems
山体滑坡 冰川崩塌
landslides, glacier collapse
甚至用于成功预测动态
even to the dynamics of prediction of success:
包括大片 YouTube视频 电影这些
blockbusters, YouTube videos, movies, and so on
但也许 它的最大应用是在金融上
But perhaps the most important application is for finance
我相信 这种理论阐明了
and this theory illuminates, I believe
我们所经历的金融危机的深层次原因
the deep reason for the financial crisis that we have gone through
这根植于30年的泡沫历史
This is rooted in 30 years of history of bubbles
从1980年开始 1987年全球泡沫破灭
starting in 1980, with the global bubble crashing in 1987
紧接着又有很多泡沫产生
followed by many other bubbles
最大的一个是 2000年破灭的新经济互联网泡沫
The biggest one was the new economy Internet bubble in 2000, crashing in 2000
之后是很多国家的房地产泡沫
the real estate bubbles in many countries
各地的金融衍生品泡沫
financial derivative bubbles everywhere
各地的股市泡沫
stock market bubbles also everywhere
商品和石油泡沫 债务和信贷泡沫
commodity and oil bubbles, debt and credit bubbles --
泡沫 泡沫 泡沫
bubbles, bubbles, bubbles
我们有一个全球泡沫
We had a global bubble
这是对全球所有市场过高估计的测量
This is a measure of global overvaluation of all markets
表示出我所说的永恒印钞机错觉
expressing what I call an illusion of a perpetual money machine
它在2007年最终崩溃
that suddenly broke in 2007
问题在于我们现在总看到相同的策略
The problem is that we see the same process
特别是通过量化宽松
in particular through quantitative easing
各国政府总想着永恒开启印钞机
of a thinking of a perpetual money machine nowadays
2008年以来的美国 欧洲 日本 都希望这样来应对危机
to tackle the crisis since 2008 in the U.S., in Europe, in Japan
这具有非常重要的意义 能帮助我们理解
This has very important implications to understand
量化宽松以及紧缩政策的失败
the failure of quantitative easing as well as austerity measures
我们并没有攻击问题的核心
as long as we don't attack the core
这种永恒印钞机思维的结构性原因
the structural cause of this perpetual money machine thinking
以上都是大的论断
Now, these are big claims
你们干嘛要相信我呢
Why would you believe me?
也许是因为在过去15年中
Well, perhaps because, in the last 15 years
我们从象牙塔中走了出来
we have come out of our ivory tower
开始发表"事前"…
and started to publish ex ante --
我强调"事前" 也就是事情发生之前
and I stress the term ex ante, it means "in advance"
在崩盘之前
before the crash
确定泡沫或金融过剩的存在
confirmed the existence of the bubble or the financial excesses
这些是近期历史中
These are a few of the major bubbles
我们经历过的一些主要泡沫
that we have lived through in recent history
它们每一个都有自己的有趣故事
Again, many interesting stories for each of them
我将只介绍一到两个我们处理大型泡沫的故事
Let me tell you just one or two stories that deal with massive bubbles
我们都知道中国奇迹
We all know the Chinese miracle
这是股市大泡沫的图示
This is the expression of the stock market of a massive bubble
短短几年间 价格指数就涨到了原来的三倍 300%
you know, a factor of three, 300% in just a few years
2007年9月
In September 2007
我被邀请到一个宏观对冲基金管理会议作主题演讲
I was invited as a keynote speaker of a macro hedge fund management conference
我在会议上展示了一个预测
and I showed to the conference a prediction
即到2007年末 这个泡沫会发生质变
that by the end of 2007, this bubble would change regime
可能会出现崩盘 不可持续是肯定的
There might be a crash. Certainly not sustainable
你们觉得这些
Now, how do you believe
极度聪明 积极上进 见多识广的宏观对冲基金经理人
the very smart, very motivated, very informed macro hedge fund managers
会对该预测作何反应
reacted to this prediction?
他们在这个泡沫上已经赚了数十亿
You know, they had made billions just surfing this bubble until now
他们跟我说 "迪迪埃 对 市场价值可能被高估了"
They told me, "Didier, yeah, the market might be overvalued
"但你忘了"
but you forget something
"2008年8月北京奥运即将开始"
There is the Beijing Olympic Games coming in August 2008
"很明显 中国政府会控制经济"
and it's very clear that the Chinese government is controlling the economy
"采取一切手段"
and doing what it takes
"来控制股市并避免任何波动"
to also avoid any wave and control the stock market"
我演讲过后三周
Three weeks after my presentation
市场损失20%
the markets lost 20 percent
经历了一番剧烈波动之后
and went through a phase of volatility, upheaval
到年底总市场价值损失70%
and a total market loss of 70 percent until the end of the year
我们为什么会集体犯下这种错误
So how can we be so collectively wrong
会误读甚至忽略这种科学事实
by misreading or ignoring the science
也就是 当不稳定发展起来 系统成熟之时
of the fact that when an instability has developed and the system is ripe
任何扰动
any perturbation
都会让整个系统无法控制
makes it essentially impossible to control?
中国市场崩溃了 但之后它又复苏了
The Chinese market collapsed, but it rebounded
2009年 我们又辨别出一个较小的新泡沫
In 2009, we also identified that this new bubble, a smaller one
是不可持续的
was unsustainable
我们又提前发布了一个预测
so we published again a prediction, in advance
说2009年8月前 市场会进行调整
stating that by August 2009, the market will correct
将不会继续原有道路
will not continue on this track
批评我们的人 读到预测后说
Our critics, reading the prediction, said
"不 这不可能"
"No, it's not possible
"有中国政府呢"
The Chinese government is there
"他们吸取了教训 他们会控制的"
They have learned their lesson. They will control
"他们也想从增长中获益"
They want to benefit from the growth"
也许没有吸取教训的是这些批评者自己
Perhaps these critics have not learned their lesson previously
危机确实发生 市场进行了调整
So the crisis did occur. The market corrected
还是之前的批评者 说 "啊 是"
The same critics then said, "Ah, yes
"但你发布了你的预测"
but you published your prediction
"你影响了市场"
You influenced the market
"这就不是预测了"
It was not a prediction"
也许我当时很有影响力
Maybe I am very powerful then
这就有趣了
Now, this is interesting
这显示出目前为止 要发展出一门经济科学几乎是不可能的
It shows that it's essentially impossible until now to develop a science of economics
因为我们都是有情感的人类 我们会去预料
because we are sentient beings who anticipate
自我应验的预言会成为问题
and there is a problem of self-fulfilling prophesies
于是我们发明了一种新的科学方法
So we invented a new way of doing science
我们创造了金融泡沫实验
We created the Financial Bubble Experiment
做法如下 我们监控市场
The idea is the following. We monitor the markets
鉴别出过剩 泡沫
We identify excesses, bubbles
我们做我们的工作 写一份报告
We do our work. We write a report
其中写有我们预计的临界时间
in which we put our prediction of the critical time
我们不发布报告 它是保密的
We don't release the report. It's kept secret
但我们会使用现代加密技术
But with modern encrypting techniques
我们使用哈希算法 我们发布一个公共密匙
we have a hash, we publish a public key
六个月后 我们再发布报告
and six months later, we release the report
而且我们还有认证
and there is authentication
所有这些都是在一个国际资料库中进行
And all this is done on an international archive
再就没有人会说我们发布的报告影响市场了
so that we cannot be accused of just releasing the successes
我再告诉你们一个最近的分析
Let me tease you with a very recent analysis
2013年5月17日 就在两周前
17th of May, 2013, just two weeks ago
我们鉴别出美国股市处在不可持续的道路上
we identified that the U.S. stock market was on an unsustainable path
5月21日 我们在自己的网站上公布
and we released this on our website on the 21st of May
市场状况会发生更迭
that there will be a change of regime
第二天 市场果然就开始发生变化
The next day, the market started to change regime, of course
这次不是崩盘
This is not a crash
这只是大型泡沫形成过程中的第三或第四次动作
This is just the third or fourth act of a massive bubble in the making
将讨论扩大到整个地球的规模 我们也看到相同现象
Scaling up the discussion at the size of the planet, we see the same thing
不管在什么地方 这都是可观测的
Wherever we look, it's observable:
在生物圈中 在大气中 在海洋中
in the biosphere, in the atmosphere, in the ocean
都有这种超指数变化轨迹
showing these super-exponential trajectories
表现出不可持续的路径 预示着相变的发生
characterizing an unsustainable path and announcing a phase transition
右侧这张图
This diagram on the right
展示了一份精美的研究
shows a very beautiful compilation of studies
未来数十年内 可能存在一个非线性的重大转变
suggesting indeed that there is a nonlinear -- possibility
for a nonlinear transition just in the next few decades
可见 泡沫到处都是
So there are bubbles everywhere
从某一方面看 这很令人兴奋
From one side, this is exciting
特别是对于我 我是一个追逐泡沫的教授 一个屠龙者
for me, as a professor who chases bubbles, and slays dragons
媒体有时这样称呼我
as the media has sometimes called me
但我们真的有能力屠龙吗
But can we really slay the dragons?
就在最近 和协作者一同
Very recently, with collaborators
我们研究了一个动态系统
we studied a dynamical system
这里龙王是这些大的循环
where you see the dragon-king as these big loops
我们能够在正确时间施加微弱调整
and we were able to apply tiny perturbations at the right times
在控制开启的条件下除掉这些龙王
that removed, when control is on, these dragons
统治是计划和预测的艺术
Governing is the art of planning and predicting
但这却是人类目前为止最大的空白领域之一
But is it not the case that this is probably one of the biggest gaps of mankind
在日益增多的挑战和危机面前
which has the responsibility to steer
我们有义务将我们的社会 我们的地球
our societies and our planet toward sustainability in the face
引向可持续发展的道路
of growing challenges and crises?
还好 龙王理论提供了希望
But the dragon-king theory gives hope
我们了解到 绝大多数系统具有可预测性
We learn that most systems have pockets of predictability
发展出先进危机诊断技术是可能的
It is possible to develop advanced diagnostics of crises
这样一来我们就能做好准备 就能采取措施
so that we can be prepared, we can take measures
就能担起责任
we can take responsibility
进而让大衰退或欧洲危机这样的极端情况
and so that never again will extremes and crises like the Great Recession
不再出乎我们意料 不再让我们不知所措
or the European crisis take us by surprise
谢谢
Thank you